Guide to the Sheldon B. Sosna Papers, 1922-2001 and undated, bulk 1948-1991 RL.01233
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Scrapbooks Series, 1947-1971 and undated, bulk 1948-1958
  - Scrapbook 1, 1947-1949 and undated (Box 7)
    Includes over 100 newspaper clippings of advertisements for Globe Fur and Novelty Company, a Chicago-based furrier marketed as Chicago's Largest Fur House.
  - Scrapbook 2, 1948-1950 and undated (Box 8)
    Includes advertising clippings and mailings for women's apparel and home construction. Apparel clients include Archie Zimmett; Bernstein, Cohen & Company; Famous Full Fashioned Hosiery Mills; Globe Fur and Novelty Company; Gold Maid Hosiery Company; Herbert Levy; McBreen Shoe Company; Misteri hosiery; Morry Silver; Sycamore Coats; U.S. Millinery Corporation; and Women's & Children's Wear Association. Construction clients include Aerosol Engineers, Aluminum Building Materials Corporation, Atlas Construction Company, and Perm-Alloy metal siding.
  - Scrapbook 3, 1948-1950 and undated (Box 9)
    Includes advertising clippings and catalog mailings, primarily representing women's apparel and home products. Apparel clients include Archie Zimmett; Berstein, Cohen & Company; Crane and Abrams; McBreen Shoe Company; and several clippings for Royal Maid featured in Women's Wear Daily. Home products clients include Atlas Construction Company; Frig-O-Matic Company; Freez King freezer (E.C.A. Manufacturing Co.); and Weathermaster windows.
  - Scrapbook 4, 1949-1950 and undated, 14 folders (Box 10)
    Includes clippings, mailings, catalogs and brochures documenting Sosna's early advertising work in Chicago. Also includes a press release announcing the Good Design exhibition sponsored jointly by The Merchandise Mart and the Museum of Modern Art, and two unlabeled/undated black and white fashion photographs.
  - Scrapbook 4, 1949-1950 and undated (Box 11)
    - Weathermaster ALSCO combination windows, 1949 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1954-1959 and undated
    - Bache & Co., undated (Box 11)
    - Bauer & Black: Curad Bandages, 1954 (Box 11)
    - Bristol-Myers: Ipana toothpaste sketches, undated, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Crane Company, circa 1955 (Box 11)
    - KVP Company, undated (Box 11)
    - Mott's Applesauce, undated (Box 11)
    - Procter & Gamble: Camay, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1954-1971 and undated (Box 11)
    Includes advertising clippings and proofs housed within original scrapbook mylar pages. Clients represented include Bache & Co.; Bristol-Myers; Crane Company; Eastman Kodak; Grant Advertising; Ladies' Home Journal; Manhattan; Martex; Pure Oil Company; Sugar Information, Inc.; and United States Tobacco Company (Encore cigarettes).
- Visual Materials Series, circa 1961-1962, 1967-1990s and undated
  Arranged into three subseries: Slides, Negatives, and Film. Contains over 700 slides Sosna used for seminar presentations conducted from the late 1970s through the 1990s, primarily focused on retail marketing strategy and supermarket advertising. Slides organized in three categories -- Seminars, Supermarket advertisements, and Other -- therein arranged alphabetically by subject/title. Seminars include slides which directly accompanied Sosna's seminar presentations on advertising and marketing strategy, and consist primarily of text. Supermarket advertisements slides include advertisements and supermarket circulars promoting event/holiday sales and specific product sales, likely used within seminar presentations yet not associated with any particular seminar. Series also includes one folder of color negatives documenting the 1967 Pabst Red beer campaign and one film reel entitled The Peace Corps which Sosna wrote, produced, and edited, circa 1961-1962. The film reel features President John F. Kennedy, Robert Sargent Shriver (Director of the Peace Corps from 1961-1966), and Dave Garroway (then host of NBC's Today Show). According to documents included in the collection, the film originally aired on American television stations and was seen by forty million people (See Writings and Speeches Series, folder one: Advertising notes and addenda, circa 1965 and undated). The collection holds the last remaining copy of this film.
  [Original film reel closed to use. Use copy available in the collection.]
  - Slides Subseries, 1970s-1990s (Box 12)
    - Seminars
      - Budgeting for Advertising (Box 12)
      - Getting the Reader to Want (Box 12)
      - How To Sell Your Advertising Ideas (Box 12)
      - How To Win With Advertising (Box 12)
      - How You Can Make the Most Out of Advertising (Box 12)
      - Information & Reward (shoppers' trends) (Box 12)
      - Market Profile Data Chart (Box 12)
      - Supermarket Advertising and the Consumer (Box 12)
      - Supermarket Futures: 90s and Beyond (Box 12)
      - Titles and headings (Box 12)
      - Using Radio (Box 12)
      - Using TV (Box 12)
      - What Shoppers Think (Box 12)
    - Supermarket advertisements
      - Event promotions
        - Back to School/Kids sales (Box 12)
        - Dollar Day promotions (Box 12)
        - Earthquake preparation/Environmental concerns (Box 12)
        - Grand Opening (Box 12)
        - Holiday and anniversary sales (Box 12)
        - Special Olympics sales (Box 12)
        - Superbowl sales (Box 12)
      - Product sales
        - Best promotions (Box 12)
        - Canned foods (Box 12)
        - Dairy/Eggs (Box 12)
        - Diet foods (Box 12)
        - Ethnic/Regional foods (Box 12)
        - Free promotions (Box 12)
        - Fresh promotions (Box 12)
        - Frozen foods (Box 12)
        - Lowest Price advertisements (Box 12)
        - Lucky/ Food Lion store promotions (Box 12)
        - Meat/Fish (Box 12)
        - Produce (Box 12)
        - Ralphs/ Vons store promotions (Box 12)
        - Sales (miscellaneous), 4 folders (Box 12)
          Features slides which promote multiple products in a single advertisement, and therefore do not fit within one particular category above.
    - Other
      - Graphic designs (Box 12)
      - Prince Spaghetti Sauce: Mona Lisa campaign (Box 12)
  - Negatives Subseries, 1967
    - Pabst Blue Ribbon: Pabst Red beer campaign, 1967 (Box 12)
      [Includes four 8"x10" color negatives used in the Pabst Red campaign.]
  - Film Reel Subseries, circa 1961-1962
    - Original Copy: The Peace Corps, circa 1961-1962 (Box 13)
      [Format: black-and-white 16mm film. TRT: 27 minutes.]
    - Master Copy (Box 12)
      [Format: BetacamSP. Created: 2005.]
    - Use copy (Box 12)
      [Format: DVD. Created: 2005.]
- Oversize Materials
  Primarily includes oversize materials from the Advertisements Series, organized into Clippings and Proofs and Sketches and Concepts Subseries. Also contains two folders from the Printed Materials Series and four folders of material removed from the Scrapbooks Series, Scrapbook 5. Clients represented include the American Tobacco Company; Bristol-Myers; Hoover appliances; Ladies' Home Journal; Martex; Pabst Brewing Company; Proctor & Gamble; Pure Oil Company; and Schlitz Brewing Company. Materials of particular interest include an advertisement proof for Ladies' Home Journal featuring President Kennedy, with the tag-line Will women love him or leave him?; a 1952 flip-chart prepared for the American Larder Supply Company entitled Now...Eat Better Food and Spend Less For It; and a pamphlet distributed by the War Advertising Council at the close of World War II. Arranged within original series, therein alphabetically by client.
  - Advertisements Series, 1954-1971 and undated (Box OV1)
    - Clippings and Proofs
      [See also Box 5]
      - Allstate Insurance, 1957 and undated (Box OV1)
      - American Tobacco Company
        - Half and Half and Montclair cigarettes, 1963-1965 (Box OV1)
        - Silva Thins cigarettes, 1967-1968 and undated (Box OV1)
      - Archway Cookies, 1959 (Box OV1)
      - Bauer & Black: Curad bandages/tape, 1954 and undated (Box OV1)
      - Bristol-Myers: Ipana toothpaste, 1961 (Box OV1)
      - Brown Shoe Company, 1957 (Box OV1)
      - Comet Rice, undated (Box OV1)
      - Grant Advertising, undated (Box OV1)
      - Hoover, 1955-1956 and undated (Box OV1)
      - International Harvester, 1955 (Box OV1)
      - Ladies' Home Journal, 1960 (Box OV1)
        [Includes advertisement proof featuring President Kennedy with the tag-line Will women love him or leave him?]
      - Leo Burnett Advertising: twentieth anniversary commemorative broadside and advertisement, 1955 (Box OV1)
        [Includes original office memorandum attached to broadside.]
      - Manhattan (sportswear), 1963-1964 (Box OV1)
      - Martex, 1971 and undated (Box OV1)
      - Pabst Brewing Company (Box OV2)
        - Old Tankard Ale, 1957 (Box OV2)
        - Pabst Blue Ribbon
          - Newspaper advertisements, various, 1956-1957 and undated (Box OV2)
          - Pabst Blue Ribbon Touch campaign, 1956 and undated (Box OV2)
          - What'll You Have campaign, 1956 and undated (Box OV2)
      - Procter & Gamble Company: Camay soap, 1957 (Box OV2)
      - Pure Oil Company, 1955-1957 and undated
        - Pure Oil Company: Barge-A-Comin' contest, 1955 (Oversize-folder Folder 1)
      - Schlitz Brewing Company: Old Milwaukee beer, 1958 (Box OV2)
      - Tea Council, 1957 (Box OV2)
      - U.S. Tobacco Company: Encore cigarettes, 1961 (Box OV2)
    - Sketches and Concepts
      [See also Box 6]
      - Appointment hosiery, undated (Box OV2)
      - Martex: Lady Pepperell designs, undated (Box OV2)
      - Pabst Brewing Company: Pabst Red, undated (Box OV2)
      - Pure Oil Company, undated (Box OV2)
      - Tennyson Menthol cigarettes, undated (Box OV2)
  - Printed Materials Series, circa 1944, 1952 (Box OV2)
    - Client Materials
      - American Larder Supply Company, Strategic Flip-Chart: Now...Eat Better Food and Spend Less For It, 1952 (Box OV2)
    - War Advertising Council, Restatement of Policy pamphlet, circa 1944 (Box OV2)
  - Scrapbooks Series, 1954-1959 and undated (Box OV2)
    - Scrapbook 5, 1954-1959 and undated
      [See also Box 11]
      - Crane Company, 1955 (Box OV2)
      - Hoover appliances, 1955, 1957 and undated (Box OV2)
      - Proctor & Gamble: Camay soap, 1957 (Box OV2)
      - Schlitz Brewing Company: Old Milwaukee beer, 1959 (Box OV2)